Gordon Schendel papers, Inclusive: 1964-1990, undated, Bulk: 1964-1970, undated
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Gordon Schendel papers
Inclusive: 1964-1990, undated, Bulk: 1964-1970, undated
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
95
Schendel, Cynthia; Schendel, Gordon; Schendel, Margaret
1 document box.
The Gordon Schendel papers consist of Schendel's notes regarding the assassination of President John F. Kennedy as well as newspaper clippings written by or about Schendel.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Gordon Schendel, a native of Minnesota, graduated from the University of Minnesota and began a career in writing and journalism starting in 1946. While working in New York City, he met a magazine artist named Margaret Waltz. The couple married and had 5 children: Cynthia, William, Eric, Amy, and Jenny.
After living on the east coast for several years, the Schendel family moved to Mexico where they remained for 11 years. During that time, Gordon worked for “The Medical Tribune” and “The Medical World News.” It was during their stay in Mexico that the Schendels became engrossed with the assassination of President John F. Kennedy. Gordon and Margaret, who often served as a fellow researcher and editor for her husband, accumulated clippings and books on the Kennedy assassination, the bulk of which now shapes the collection here at Poage Library. Despite his intentions, Gordon was never able to use his research and complete a book on the topic.
Gordon Schendel did, however, write several books during his career including “Jungle Wife,” — which recounted the life of an Estonian jaguar hunter and his American wife during their stay in Brazil; “The Higher They Go,” — a biography of former New York City mayor William O’Dwyer; and “Medicine in Mexico: From Aztec Herbs to Betatrons.”
In 1965, the Schendels moved to McAllen, Texas, where Gordon joined the editorial staff of the local newspaper, the “Valley Evening Monitor.” After the passing of her parents, the Schendels’ daughter, Cynthia, donated the collection in August 2013.
Scope and Content
The Gordon Schendel papers range in chronology from 1964 to 1990 with several undated documents. The bulk of the materials date from the late 1960's since they concern the assassination of President John F. Kennedy which took place on November 22, 1963.
Most of the materials are notes, both typed and handwritten, produced by Gordon Schendel in connection to the investigation of John F. Kennedy's assassination. The Notes series is arranged alphabetically by topic and addresses several of the major characters surrounding the case including Lee Harvey Oswald, Jack Ruby, and the Warren Commission.
In addition to Schendel's research notes, there are also three folders of clippings that contain more information on John F. Kennedy, an article written by Gordon Schendel on his experiences living in Mexico, and an article written about Gordon Schendel when he joined the staff of McAllen, Texas's newspaper, the "Valley Evening Monitor." Overall, the materials in the collection range from average to good condition.
Arrangement
Prior to this current round of processing, the collection was housed in acid-free folders with descriptive titles and date ranges. An inventory was created when the initial gift was donated in August 2013, but no finding aid existed.
The original order of the collection has largely been maintained. Two series were created based on material type: I. Clippings and II. Notes. Within these two respective series, folders are arranged alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 95. Acquired 2013-08-01
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. “Margaret Waltz Schendel.” Memorial #97304434. Databases. Accessed August 26, 2020.
Gordon Schendel papers, Accession #95, Control File, Baylor Collection of Political Materials, W. R. Poage Legislative Library, Baylor University.
“Writing Can Be Dangerous, Newcomer to McAllen Says”, “Valley Evening Monitor”, February 14, 1965.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Assassination.; Oswald, Lee Harvey.; Schendel, Gordon.; Schendel, Margaret.
Places
Mexico -- History.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Research notes.
- Clippings, 1964-1966; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Series I. Clippings is comprised of three folders. The first is a folder of general clippings relating to President John F. Kennedy's assassination. The second folder contains an article written by Gordon Schendel concerning his experiences in the town of San Miguel de Allende, Mexico. The third and final folder holds an article written about Gordon Schendel when he accepted an editorial position for McAllen, Texas's newspaper, the "Valley Evening Monitor." This folder is particularly helpful as it contains biographical information on Gordon Schendel. Overall, these materials are in good condition. Most of the clippings have been photocopied onto acid-free paper.
  - General, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Article, "A Medieval Town", Gordon Schendel, 1966 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Article, "Writing Can Be Dangerous, Newcomer to McAllen Says", 1965 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Notes, 1964-1990, undated; 2
  General condition: Average.
  Series II. Notes, the largest series in the collection, contains research materials that Gordon and Margaret Schendel collected concerning the assassination of President John F. Kennedy. The folders are organized alphabetically by topic. Most subjects are individuals who were involved in the assassination - including Lee Harvey Oswald and Jack Ruby - or in the investigation afterwards (i. e. the Warren Commission). The materials in this series are in average condition.
  - General, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ballistics, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carol Miller, "Life", 1964 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clayton Hickerson, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Diagrams by Margaret Schendel, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Facts and Revelations", Morris Bealle, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ian Fleming, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Incubus, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jack Ruby, 1964 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jim Garrison, Statements, 1968 January (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - John F. Kennedy Memorial Library, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - John Pillion, Press Releases, 1964 September (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kennedy Administration, Achievements, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lee Harvey Oswald, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Marilyn Monroe, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Right-Wing Conspiracy, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Saturday Evening Post", 1964 October (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Speculations, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Warren Commission, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)